<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>August II. 1622. A remonstration of the French subiects professing the reformed religion vnto the French King Wherein are showne divers notable passages, and matters of great waight and consideration, as well of the present as of the former troubles and dissentions in France. As also, a relation, containing the rebellion of the nobilitie and gentrie of the kingdome of Naples, and the retreate of the Vice-Roy. The sea-fight betwixt the gallies of Spaine, and Florence, and some pirates. The resolution of Bethlem Gabor ... The arrivall of Sir Robert Sherley at Florence, being sent ambassassador [sic] from the King of Persia. Besides the late proceedings of the Duke of Saxony ... Of the Count Mansfeild, and the Duke Christian of Brunswick; as likewise what Spinola determines to do, and hath done, before Breda, Bergen op Zoon, and Sluce. ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.69</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>August II. 1622. A remonstration of the French subiects professing the reformed religion vnto the French King Wherein are showne divers notable passages, and matters of great waight and consideration, as well of the present as of the former troubles and dissentions in France. As also, a relation, containing the rebellion of the nobilitie and gentrie of the kingdome of Naples, and the retreate of the Vice-Roy. The sea-fight betwixt the gallies of Spaine, and Florence, and some pirates. The resolution of Bethlem Gabor ... The arrivall of Sir Robert Sherley at Florence, being sent ambassassador [sic] from the King of Persia. Besides the late proceedings of the Duke of Saxony ... Of the Count Mansfeild, and the Duke Christian of Brunswick; as likewise what Spinola determines to do, and hath done, before Breda, Bergen op Zoon, and Sluce. ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at their shops at the Exchange, and in Popes-head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11307 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:1"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRATION OF THE FRENCH SVBIECTS Profeſſing the Reformed Religion <hi>vnto the French</hi> KING. Wherein are ſhowne divers notable Paſſages, and matters of great waight and conſideration, <hi>as well of the preſent as of the former</hi> Troubles and Diſſentions in <hi>France. As alſo</hi> A Relation, containing the Rebellion of the Nobilitie and Gentrie of the Kingdome of NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLES, and the Retreate of the VICE-ROY. The Sea-fight betwixt the Gallies of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> and ſome Pirates. The Reſolution of <hi>Bethlem Gabor;</hi> beſides divers Lords of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſent in writing vnto the <hi>Emperour.</hi> The Arrivall of Sir ROBERT SHERLEY at <hi>Florence,</hi> being ſent Ambaſſaſſador from the King of PERSIA. <hi>Beſides</hi> The late Proceedings of the Duke of SAXONY, being forſaken by his owne Souldiers, who were vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to goe againſt the Proteſtants. Of the Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> and the Duke <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of <hi>Brunſwick;</hi> as likewiſe what <hi>Spinola</hi> determines to do, and hath done, before <hi>Breda, Bergen op Zoon,</hi> and <hi>Sluce. With</hi> A continuance of the late Newes of all parts of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and ſome parts of <hi>Turkey</hi> likewiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and in <hi>Popes</hi>-head <hi>Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2745:2"/>
            <head>A REMONSTRATION Of the French Subiects, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Reformed Religion, vnto the French KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſtrange, and almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, that amongſt ſo many Subiects (which God hath beene pleaſed to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vnder the obeyſance of your Maieſtie) who boaſt ordinarily, that they are much affected to the good of your affaires, &amp; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of your Crowne; that nevertheleſſe, there hath not beene one, which hath endevoured and enforced himſelfe, to quench the fire which takes daily hold of your State, and by little and little conſumes the ſame: and that to the contrary, there is found a great number that haue taken great paines to adde more fewell to it, and are yet daily ſeeking artificiall tricks and deviſes to maintaine and increaſe the ſame. By right, it ſhould be their worke, who can make Peace and Warre when they pleaſe, if their private ends, and particular profit which made them to raiſe thoſe troubles, contrary to the minde and intention of your Maieſtie,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2745:3"/>did not draw them backe, and not of thoſe which are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted and purſued in their conſciences, honors, goods, and liues, and haue no other intention then to defend and preſerue themſelues from violences, having never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted any thing more then troubles, and ſeditious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions; and to the contrary, nothing more loved and procured, then the conſervation of Peace. Wherefore, all the Lords, Gentlemen, and all your Maieſties other Subiects that follow them, making profeſſion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, moved and driven by the affection and naturall Obligation that they owe vnto your Maieſtie, and to the conſervation of your Kingdome, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could or would vſe any longer delay, for to ſeeke and propoune of their ſide (as they haue done continually) all the fit and convenient meanes they could deviſe, to preſerue your State from ruine and ſubverſion, which haue threatned the ſame many times, and yet at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent doe more then ever before, and to reeſtabliſh a good Peace and publique tranquillitie, who having continually ſhewed themſelues prompt and willing to embrace the ſame, it is manifeſt enough, in what dangers and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences they were likely to fall, if God through his meere mercie had not preſerved them. In ſuch manner that they haue but ſmall hope, to come to their deſire, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Almightie God, will be pleaſed to chauge the hearts of their enemies, which are round about you, and incline them to a pacification, or Peace. Looking ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that this their good diſpoſition which they now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and their endevours which they will vſe, for to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a firme and perfect Vnion betwixt all your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, both of the one and the other Religion, in ſtead of being received and embraced. ſhall be ſlandered, and ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly interpreted, as they haue beene continually, by thoſe which hate and feare nothing more then this recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. That nevertheleſſe, the ſayd Lords, Gentlemen, and other that follow them, having continually taken great care, to make their actions daily more and more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2745:3"/>vnto your Maieſtie, and to leaue aſſured ſignes and witneſſes of their deſire, which is to liue and die in the obedience, and naturall ſubiection which they owe vnto your Maieſtie, and to make it appeare to all the world, how much their hearts and wills are differing from the impoſtures and ſlanders, which their adverſaries, adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and miniſters lay vpon them; and that the Forces which they haue beene compelled to gather againſt their mindes, doe tend to no other effect then to maintaine and conſerue their Religion, honours, liues, and goods. They haue thought that ſuch conſiderations ought not to hinder or ſtay them in their hunting and purchaſing the effect of ſuch a neceſſary, and ſalutary a Peace for this Kingdome, and to giue witneſſe of their humilitie, reverence, and reſpect towards your Maieſtie, which they would haue ſooner done, if they had not eſteemed and iudged that their enemies would haue thought, or at leaſt haue gone about to make others beleeue, that the neceſſitie had compelled them vnto the ſame, conſidering their Enemies aſſured your Maieſtie, that they were not likely to receiue any ayde from forraigne partes, and if they ſhould, that they had no money to giue them content. But it is certaine and known that they never haue wanted aide and ſuccour from aboue, and that their forces are ſuch that none can denie, but that they are able to reſiſt their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to execute ſuch ill deſignes if they would as they are taxed withall. So then in the time of the firſt troubles or Civill Warres the deceaſed Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> beſides the Lords, Gentlemen and other that did accompany him, did receiue and accept of the conditions of Peace, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning onely the Religion and the libertie of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: preſently after the death of the late Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the Marſhall of Saint <hi>Andrew,</hi> and the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of the late Conſtable <hi>Montmorancy,</hi> which were the principall heads and conductors of the Armie. If in the ſecond troubles, as ſoone as was offered vnto the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and his followers and parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2745:4"/>the reſtabliſhing of the exerciſe of their Religion, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they were affiſted mightily by forraigne forces and readie to aſſault the Towne of <hi>Chartres,</hi> at the ſight of their Enemies campe, which was moſt wholy disbanded and diſordered; And that onely at the denun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of Peace, made by a Trumpet ſent in the Kings name, the ſayd Prince did not onely ſurceaſe from the aſſault in hand, but commaunded the fiege wholy to be raiſed, and his Armie to retyre, reporting nevertheleſſe no other reward for his prompt obedience, then a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die peace, full of perfidiouſnes. If in the ſayde troubles the next day after the Battaile at Saint <hi>Denis,</hi> the ſayd Prince did ſend vnto the King <hi>Monſieur de Tiligny,</hi> to ſhew his Maieſtie, the ruine and deſolation that was likely to fall vpon this Kingdome, if it were ſuffered that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne forces ſhould invade the ſame, which were vpon the frontiers readie to enter, and to propoſe and ſhew the meanes, and remedies to attaine a peace, touching one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters of Religion, Notwithſtanding hee had the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hand in the ſayd battle; the late Conſtable <hi>Montmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy</hi> chiefe of the Armie there being flaine. To be ſhort, if all your Edicts had beene alwayes made, and the peace agreed, in thoſe ſeaſons when thoſe of the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had meanes by their forces to make their Enemies belieue them, if they would haue abuſed the ſame, and that in al their parlies &amp; treaties of peace, there is no mention made of any thing elſe then of matters of Religion, and that their Enemies haue never beene brought to a peace or pacification, but by neceſſitie, being not able by open force to attempt any thing more againſt them; Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to overcome more manifeſtly their adverſaries, of the ſlaunders and impoſtures which they publiſh every houre againſt the ſaid Lords, Gentlemen, and others that follow them, willingly paſſing by the vnfaithfulnes, want of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, &amp; deſloyalty, vſed and practiſed againſt them in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time. They declare &amp; proteſt this day before your Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſty, as before God, that howſoever they haue vntill this
<pb facs="tcp:2745:4"/>time been dealt withal, that they neuertheleſſe neuer thought to impute it vnto your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> as very well knowing, that your <hi>Maieſties</hi> nature is not agreeing with ſuch rigours, wherof you haue ſhewed ſo many open demonſtrations, that none rightly may doubt of it: and much leſſe haue they deſired to change, or diminiſh in any manner the good will, and naturall affection, which they haue borne continually to the conſeruation, aduancement &amp; greatnes of your State. And if by all the effects aforeſaid, it hath been ſeene and knowne manifeſtly, that they had neuer any ſcope nor intention, then to ſerue God according to his command, and the inſtruction of his holy word, vnder the obedience and authority of your Acts, and Proclamations, and to be maintained, and preſerued equally with your other Subiects, in their honours, lifes, and goods; but beſides this they will at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, make ſuch a proofe and tryall; that their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelues, will neuer doubt of it or call the ſame in queſtion, not that they intend to go about to iuſtifie their former actions. And much leſſe doe they intend to copitulate with your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> very well knowing by the grace of God, what is the duty of good and faithfull Subiects towards their <hi>Soneraine Prince</hi> and naturall <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir becauſe it is ſufficiently knowne how they <hi>valewe iour,</hi> faith and words, which ought to be holy, ſacred and inuiolable, and with what boldneſſe haue they abuſed your name and authority, to the great perill and danger of your Subiects, which make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Reformed Religion, it will not bee thought ſtrange that the ſame in all humble manner beſeech your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to bee pleaſed to declare by a ſolemnell, perpetuall, and irreuocable Edict, verified
<pb facs="tcp:2745:5"/>and regiſtred in all your Parlements, and other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerain Courts, of Iuſtices, to the end that by the ſame thoſe may be bridled and kept in, which ſo many times herebefore haue beene ſo bold as to infringe and violate them (and that without any puniſhment) which the late <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> of happy memory, your Father had made, and your ſelfe confirmed. And ſeeing that theſe wich neuer could endure the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and reſt amongſt your Subiects, cauſed by the meanes of the obſeruation of the ſaid Edicts, they haue begunne to alter and corrupt the ſame by new interruptions; and modifications directely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſubſtance of the ſaid Edicts, and the intention of your <hi>Maieſty.</hi> They very humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to grant and agree generally vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all your Subiects, of what quality or condition ſoeuer they be, free exerciſe of the ſaid Religion in all Cities, Townes, villages, and boroughs in all places and parts of your Kingdome, and territories vnder your obedience and protection, without any exception or reſeruation, modification or reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perſons, of time, or places, with all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances thereunto neceſſary and required.</p>
            <p>And there aboue to order and inioyne euery one to make publike profeſſion either of the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion, to the intent that many abuſing this benefice and grace may not fallitno Atheiſme, and earnall liberty, licenſing themſelues of all exerciſe and profeſſion of Religion, and not deſiring any thing elſe but that all good orders, the policy, and Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline be quite reenuerſed and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. A thing certainly too dangerous and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and vnſufferable.</p>
            <p>And further, SIR, ſeeing your ſaid ſubiectis
<pb facs="tcp:2745:5"/>doe not doubt, that thoſe which alwaies haue built the foundation of their deſſeings vpon Flanders, and calumniations which they very impudently publiſh to make them odious not onely to their party, but likewiſe to other, ſhall not leaue to diuulge, that your ſaid Subiects will rather wilfully without any reaſon defend that which they haue once reſolued to belieue, concerning the Articles of the Chriſtian Religion, then to correct themſelues and retreate any point: They declare and proteſt as they haue euer done, that if in any article of their confeſſion of faith they can inſtruct them by the word of God comprehended in the Canonicall bookes of the Scripture: That they runne aſtray from the doctrine of the Prophes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. That preſently their will ſhake hands with them, and be of they opinion and ſide that ſhall teach them better out of Gods word; and long agoe they ſhould haue done the ſame if any error had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in their articles.</p>
            <p>And to this effect they deſire nothing more, then a meeting at a free, generall, and lawfully called Councell. Where euery one may be heard, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his reaſons, which ſhall bee confirmed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted by Gods word alone. Which is the only courſe taken in antient times in all like occaſions.</p>
            <p>By this meanes SIR, you ſhall bee ſure that God will ſhew your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> this fauour that you ſhall ſee ſhortly the heartes and mindes of your Subiects v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited and reconciled, and your Kingdome to returne in the former eſtate brightneſſe and dignity: to the ſhame and confuſion of your and our enemies, which haue endeauoured the contrary.</p>
            <p>Moreouer your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> will bee pleaſed to take the paines, and conſider exactely and iudge (if you
<pb facs="tcp:2745:6"/>bee ſo diſpoſed) if it be better to tarry for a heauy and bloudie victory of the two armies, that are now in your Kingdome, wherein the conquerour is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to looſe as hee that ſhall be vanquiſhed. Or elſe to imploy them in the ſeruice of your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and for the good of our owne affaires, vpon diuers faire occaſions daily offered, ſo much concerning the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity and conſeruation of your Crown as none are comparable vnto the ſame that haue beene preſented in our time:</p>
            <p>And by theſe meanes to ſend the tempeſt, and foule weather in theſe places, from whence it came. Whereunto your aforeſaid Subiects are reſolued, as likewiſe to all other things that ſhall tend to your good and the greatneſſe of your State being readie to imploy to the ſame effect all their eſtates, and meanes, which God hath pleaſed to grant them, beſides their bodies to their vttermoſt power. Not acknowledging in this world any other Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raing or Principalites then yours: in which obedience and ſubiection they will liue and die, as your moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, moſt faithfull, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Seruants, and Subiects.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> 30. 1622.</head>
            <p>FRom <hi>Rome</hi> they write, that there came an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Embaſſador from the new Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> called the <hi>Prince di Sant Gregorio,</hi> who came very well accompanied with all the noble Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and diuers others Charactered <hi>Baroni Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> to haue audience of the Pope; now <hi>Gregory</hi> the 11. and tender all obedience and ſeruice in the name of the new Duke his Lord: hither came alſo the Sunday following, an Embaſſador from the Arch-duke <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> requeſting his holineſſe, that whereas he had certaine Souldiers in pay in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> for the Emperor, vnder the command of <hi>Don Pedro Aldabrandino,</hi> it would pleaſe his holineſſe to write vnto the Emperor, that they might be turned ouer vnto his ſeruice, to defend his Country of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia</hi> againſt the inroades, and aſſaults of ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as now lie at the aduantage to ſurpriſe ſuch Townes, as are weake, and not able to defend themſelues:</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe written, that the Monday follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, after the Embaſſador came from the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Pope went in perſon to the Conſiſtory, and there transferred vpon the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> the office and dignity of <hi>Confalonire,</hi> of the holy mother <hi>Church,</hi> as his Father had before enioyed; they will likewiſe haue certaine <hi>Cardinals,</hi> commanded to keepe their Pallaces as priſoners, for ſpeaking irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently againſt the Bull, which was newlly made for the ſtrict Election of the <hi>Popes:</hi> on the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday following, his holineſſe did keepe his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpro</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2745:7"/>in <hi>Saint Peters,</hi> and in the morning with all ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, and pontificially hee entred the ſacred Colledge before the <hi>Embaſſador</hi> of his <hi>Catholike Maieſty,</hi> where acknowledgement was made to his holineſſe for the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the payment of 7000. crownes for that feude or feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was ratified, and accepted with the accuſtomed manner of proteſtation made to the Procurator of the Exchecker; after which the whole ſigniory of of the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> to keepe correſpondency with the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> ſent vnto him no Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador; the Marqueſſe of <hi>Lanti</hi> in the name of the whole Senate: At the ſame time there died alſo in the City <hi>Signior Peter Nati,</hi> the agent of the Duke of <hi>Vrbine,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Brugnati,</hi> with ſome others of good account.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Florence</hi> they write concerning the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Count de montein,</hi> by the road of <hi>Leuca</hi> and <hi>Piſa,</hi> and that hee tooke the way of <hi>Legorne</hi> to be embarked in the Galley of <hi>Doria,</hi> to goe to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> and from thence his Excellency would paſſe to <hi>Millaine.</hi> It is alſo reported, that there is arriued at <hi>Florence</hi> the <hi>Engliſh, Sir Robert Sherley</hi> (with his Lady) called <hi>Il Conte de Sherley,</hi> as being an Earle of the <hi>Empire,</hi> his traine was not very great, and yet hee is ſent as honourable <hi>Embaſſador</hi> from the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> to the <hi>Emperor,</hi> the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> and other <hi>Princes,</hi> hauing great credit, and meanes for money and magnificent expences.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Madrid</hi> they aduiſe vs, that the <hi>Marqueſſe di ſurego,</hi> and <hi>Don diego meſſia</hi> are declared Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of Warre for the King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> as alſo the <hi>Marqueſſe de la Nueuas,</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe dimirable,</hi> and the <hi>Count di Baraſciar,</hi> are made Maſters of the
<pb facs="tcp:2745:7"/>Kings Houſe, and of the Queenes ſide or Pallace, are likewiſe named, <hi>Don diego Bazzero: Don Gaebriel de Velaſio: Don Antonio de Toledo,</hi> and <hi>Don Emanuel manriques.</hi> It is further written, that <hi>Don Inico Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> is created Generall of the Horſe in <hi>Flanders,</hi> with intent to paſſe, if occaſion ſerue, into other parts: and that the Biſhopricke of <hi>Ieguenza</hi> is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon a brother of the Duke <hi>de Infantado.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Naples</hi> are diuers Letters: one writes of a great rebellion by the Gentlemen and Nobility of the Countrey, wherein the Viceroy was enforced to take the City of Saint <hi>Erma,</hi> another talks of <hi>Leuca</hi> that the <hi>Cardinall Beuilaqua</hi> comming thither to the Bathes, and expecting the gouernment of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, was at laſt by the Nobles and Gentiles ſo confirmed, and all his kindred aduanced to places and offices. A third letter affirmes, that there depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from that Port many Gallies full of Souldiers to be embarked at <hi>Cortary,</hi> and ſo to goe into <hi>Spaine;</hi> and that there was a generall impoſition of 400000. crownes vpon the City and Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> as alſo of 150000. from the City of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and all for the ſeruice of the VVarre of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, that <hi>Don Francis Manriques</hi> was made Leutenant of the Galleies of <hi>Naples,</hi> or if you will of a ſquadron ſo named in the place of <hi>Don Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Zaphata,</hi> who was aduanced to bee M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of the campe, and ſent a 1000. <hi>Spainiards</hi> in the ſaid Gallies to <hi>Milane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Meſſina</hi> they aduertiſe vs, that the Gallies of <hi>Florence</hi> are ioyned with the King, and ſo ſet vpon ſom Pirates, with 250. ſlaues in 15. veſſels great, and ſmall, &amp; 8. peeces of braſſe, which they enforced ſincking moſt of them: the reſt made a compoſition
<pb facs="tcp:2745:8"/>for their liues paying a 100000 crownes they alſo tooke a ſhip loaden with oile at the firſt ſight.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Venice</hi> they write, that in the diet of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> (according to the Letters of <hi>Vienna</hi>) the Eſtates could not agree, but were at great variance; the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Eccleſiaſticall perſons demanding the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all their goods, loſſes, and reuenues wholly, without further impeachment. The ſecular Lords and Laity would by no means conſent to ſuch an account, pretending many diminutions, and that the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was reſerued for the good of the Kingdom: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the <hi>Catholikes</hi> appeale to the <hi>Emperor,</hi> as their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Iudge, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> on the contrary ſide, will haue none but the <hi>Palatine:</hi> inſomuch that the Emperor with all expedition ſent the <hi>Count de Soler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> to acquaint him with the matter, that hee might vſe the greater haſt in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the tributes vnder his gouernment, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his <hi>Imperiall Maieſty,</hi> who had newly ſent 2000. Horſe to the Duke of <hi>Bauaria.</hi> He alſo writ, that the wife of <hi>Oleatſi,</hi> in whoſe cuſtody was the fortreſſe of <hi>Trezin,</hi> where the Crowne of <hi>Hungary</hi> was ſecured, would by no meanes depart with the ſame, or conſent to the deliuery, before ſhee was paid ſuch money and treaſure, which had bin disburſed &amp; inforced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Genoa</hi> the aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, that with althoſe Gallaies, which are returned from <hi>Faigne,</hi> there came in their company the <hi>nuntio Acquauiua</hi> am Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>Lenta,</hi> who was ſent from the <hi>Sophy</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> in a ſhip of <hi>Legorne,</hi> which diſembarked it ſelfe at <hi>Iauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naleggio</hi> without touching <hi>Geuoa</hi> at all, and ſo they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to go to <hi>Florence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rome,</hi> yet he landed at <hi>Genoa Il Padre Iacinto nata Caſaleſio Capucino,</hi> who halfe a yeer ſince was imployed in <hi>Spaine,</hi> for the affaires of <hi>Bauaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2745:8"/>
            <p>From <hi>Coyra</hi> they write, that the partie, or faction of that Cittie were followed by a great number of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of <hi>Baldirone,</hi> who mutined for want of meanes to maintaine them, and ſo complained on the Captaines for releaſing the Priſoners, and making what compoſition they pleaſed, whereas yet they were intertained by the <hi>Grizons,</hi> and ſetled in <hi>Chiavena,</hi> to defend them from the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> but at laſt, the Biſhop was layd hold vpon, and had a Guard over him, and <hi>Baldirone</hi> ſhould haue beene ſent to Priſon, but that he eſcaped in an vnknowne habit, and ſo freed himſelfe of his enemies.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Turnie</hi> they write, that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> hath rayſed many Forces from as many places of <hi>France, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> cauſing them to come the way of the mountaine: Wherevpon his Highneſſe hath ſent his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giners, and Pioners to ſuperviſe the Fortreſſes of <hi>Aſti, Vercelles, Sanchia,</hi> and <hi>San German.</hi> Moreover, he hath ſupplied the Garriſons of <hi>Aſti,</hi> and <hi>Vercelles,</hi> with foure hundred Souldiers, and added greatquantitie of proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both of powder, ſhot, and victuall, fit for a warre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, which when they of <hi>Montferrate</hi> vnderſtood, they made interceſſion to be ſo armed, and defended accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, pretending chiefely, leaſt ſome ſodaine innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might fall vpon them</p>
            <p>One thing is certaine, that about the Countries of <hi>Aldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtera,</hi> and Confines of <hi>Savoy,</hi> you haue great numbers aſſembled, who came to the aſſiſtance, and ſervice of his Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Millane</hi> they write, that having a generall ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the revolt of the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and that the <hi>Switzers</hi> would helpe the <hi>Grizons</hi> all they could; there was a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Carts loden with the Munition of Warre ſent to the Garriſons, leaſt they ſhould be ſet vpon by their enemies, as the Dutch Souldiers had beene in the Count of <hi>Tiroll,</hi> which were there Muſtred for the Archduke <hi>Leopaldus:</hi> For queſtionleſſe, the <hi>Grizons</hi> were divided into many troops, and gone to the ſide of <hi>Pochiana,</hi> to performe ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2745:9"/>exployt vpon the Fortreſſe, where <hi>Don Iohn de Medici</hi> commanded: but finding ſome reſiſtance, and that as they were readie to enter, other troops came to relieue them, they deſiſted for feare they were too weake to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with both at once; that is to ſay, with the Fort, and this other ſupply, and ſo returned toward the Fort <hi>Di Santa Maria,</hi> which belongs to the Archduke <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paldus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Letters advertiſe vs, that the Cittie of <hi>Millane</hi> is compelled to her proportioned contribution, being about 40000. Crownes, not onely for this yeare, but to a monethly allowance for the next yeare 1623. and that all the Citties within that Territory, haue likewiſe their ſeverall Collections to maintaine the warres. That the money ſent to the Catholique <hi>Switzers,</hi> hath beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed to good purpoſe, becauſe they haue ſtopped that Paſſage, by which the Proteſtant <hi>Switzers</hi> meant to goe and aſſiſt the <hi>Grizons,</hi> wherevpon there was a new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſement made of a 100000 Crownes to pay thoſe <hi>Switzers,</hi> who were vnder Colonell <hi>Berlinghier,</hi> part in full ſatisfaction, and part in way of a new aſſignation. That the Souldiers of the Knight <hi>Pecchio,</hi> being returned out of <hi>Alſatia,</hi> were ſent to remaine in <hi>Bornio,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> reſident in <hi>Chiavana</hi> returned alſo to <hi>Millane,</hi> ſo that there remained onely in theſe parts the Count <hi>Iohn Sherbolone,</hi> and his troops. That many Souldiers are fled out of the <hi>Valtoline</hi> for want of pay, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, who notwithſtanding, are a new lifted in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment</hi> of Count <hi>Franciſo d' Adda,</hi> who is deputed to make an end of the buſineſſe. That there is returned out of <hi>Alſatia</hi> to <hi>Millane,</hi> the Marquis <hi>De Valdefuentes,</hi> and from <hi>Tiroll</hi> the Captaine, <hi>Iohn Baptiſta Panteor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la,</hi> after they had given order to leavie eleven Companies of Horſe, and make other proviſion for the Souldiers, which they alſo performed with all diligence in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Salz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgh,</hi> to maintaine and perfect the government of Count <hi>di Lodron,</hi> whoſe Regiment was not yet full enough. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2745:9"/>that the Fmbaſſadour extraordinary of <hi>Mantua,</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a paſſage for certaine Souldiers, who were to goe from <hi>Mantua</hi> to <hi>Monſferrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the death of the great <hi>Turke</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new confirmed. It ſeemes, the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his death, but that it was onely contrived by a <hi>Vicebaſſhaw,</hi> Generall at the Sea, or as we call <hi>Admirall,</hi> who vnderhand writ a Letter to the <hi>Baſſhaw</hi> of <hi>Gran Cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> that the <hi>Turke</hi> meant to come thither, &amp; alter the forme of Government, for the ſuppreſſing the inſolency of the <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> to which purpoſe, he was reſolved to denie them their donation. This Letter was found by chance, but ſo found, that the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> tooke notice of the ſame, and ſuppoſing it true, were ſo enraged, that they adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured vpon the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> and ſo one rage helping forward another, the Devill ſet them aworke (as you haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly heard) but at laſt the <hi>Viceers</hi> vnderſtanding all the matter, found a time to make the other <hi>Ianizaries</hi> acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the treaſon, and promiſe them the augmentation of three <hi>aſpers</hi> a day, which the great <hi>Sultana,</hi> the mother of <hi>Oſman,</hi> being retired to <hi>Milo,</hi> with her <hi>Spahies,</hi> and and certaine <hi>Chauſes,</hi> confirmed. Whereupon the greater ſort of <hi>Ianizaries</hi> came preſently to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that the great <hi>Empreſſe</hi> lay ſafe in the Iland of <hi>Mile,</hi> that there were three brothers aliue of the ſlaughtered <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and that there were alſo two <hi>Sultana's</hi> of his owne great with childe, and which the <hi>Mufti</hi> knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: Thus new tumults aroſe in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the ſhopps ſhutt, nor the government altred, nor any ſtranger diſturbed; in the midſt of which Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, comes the <hi>Admirall</hi> of the Gallies to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> vpon whom in a fury the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> layd hands, who made what reſiſtance he could, and ſo at laſt he was burnt with 18. Gallies: yet for the time is <hi>Muſtapha</hi> confirmed, and is like to continue, vnleſſe they ſuſpect his weakeneſſe and vnaptneſſe to ſuch a government, and will no doubt, and ſo make choiſe of ſome braue Spirit, to guide the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2745:10"/>of this vnruly Chariot of the Turkiſh Empire, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at leaſt fiftie ſeverall Provinces, ſuch as in times paſt were reputed Kingdomes of reaſonable eminency, and opulent mightineſſe.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Franckefort,</hi> the old Letters confirme the defeate of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> who is named in the ſame the Biſhop of <hi>Haverſtate,</hi> and this is their Language: that there paſſed by this City 132. Cornets of horſe, and 128. Enſignes of foote, belonging to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and were quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnited to Monſieur <hi>Tillies</hi> forces, who defeated the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop at the River of <hi>Maine,</hi> to the loſſe of 3000. beſides 1000. drownd in the River of <hi>Maine;</hi> his cariages were moſt ſurpriſed, and ſome money taken, there were alſo taken priſoners the Count of <hi>Lipſtat,</hi> and <hi>Sturnne,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Vannas,</hi> after which the Armie of <hi>Tilley</hi> reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Holſt</hi> againe, and put ſome to death, which made reſiſtance: here they found two or three peeces of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery: not withſtanding all this? <hi>Brunſwick</hi> eſcaped with full 10000. into <hi>Darmſtrat,</hi> where hee vnited himſelfe to Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> who taking their marches to <hi>Bergſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> encountred with 300. horſe of <hi>Crovata,</hi> who were al cut in peeces: this Letter was writt from one, who was willing to ſhew his good will, but had not the Fortune of true intelligence, but we had this newes long agoe.</p>
            <p>The newer Letters, which came the 24. of Iuly, certefie thus much, that both <hi>Bavaria</hi> and <hi>Tilley</hi> are retyred out of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> holding their quarters about the Mountaines beyond <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> and ſo meane to ſtop the paſſage into <hi>Bavaria:</hi> and the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with <hi>Mansfeild</hi> are alſo gone out of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> the King went to <hi>Sedan</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Bolloigne:</hi> His Generall or Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> marching openly with cullours diſplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed even to the borders of <hi>Loraine,</hi> and <hi>Lutzenbergh,</hi> and all attending the treaty at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where if it be peace, It is ſuppoſed, that <hi>Mansfeild</hi> eyther enters into the ſervice of the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> or adventures into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Lipſia</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Letters containe, that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2745:10"/>Elector Duke vpon the Certificate of the Emperour, hath raiſed together 22000. protecting ſomething of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence for his owne honour, and the Emperours ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, but as he was in his march, both horſe and foote fell from him and reſolved him peremptorily, that they would goe and aſſiſt the Biſhop of <hi>Haverſplate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Prague</hi> the Letters adviſe, that thoſe Countrie men, which were ſuppoſed to be cut in peeces by the <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks</hi> in their returne, were indeede overthrowne by the ſouldiers of <hi>Glats,</hi> who in a braue and reſolute ſally ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Enemies, and tooke many priſoners and a great booty, forraging the Country, and killing all, that reſiſted them, returning with their ſpoyles to their hold of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and as it ſhould ſeeme being thereby emboldened to hold it out againſt the greateſt perill.</p>
            <p>From <hi>France</hi> they write, that how ever the Kings armie prevayled in the ſiege of Saint <hi>Anthony,</hi> yet was <hi>Montal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> relieved, &amp; had many ſupplies, ſo that it is not thought convenient, that the King ſhould hazard his perſon againſt any of theſe great Townes; but they ſay, as hee was marching foreward, the Duke <hi>de Rohan,</hi> ſet vpon ſome of his Army, and put them to defeate.</p>
            <p>That the Queene Mother went from <hi>Nantes</hi> toward the Bathes of <hi>Pughes</hi> neere vnto <hi>Nevers:</hi> That the King hath graunted to Signeur <hi>Pempeio Frangipane</hi> 2000. crownes, as a penſion out of the Abbey where his brother was Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot: who now deceaſed and the place voyd, it pleaſed his Maieſtie to diſpoſe of ſome of the revenues in this maner: and that the Cardinall <hi>Bevilacqua</hi> was at the ſayd Bathes, but hearing of the Queenes approch made haſt to depart into his owne Country.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Antwarp</hi> they write, that on Sunday the 21. of Iuly. The Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> was attended thither with 2000. horſe, and the Nobilitie of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant:</hi> having before hand taken order, that the Governour of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2745:11"/>
               <hi>Gaunt</hi> ſhould viſite <hi>Sluice,</hi> and build 4. ſeverall Forts, as neere it as they could, that ſo they might bee aſſured hee meant once againe to beſiege the ſame: For they giue it out, he will haue three Armies afoote this Summer: one againſt <hi>Sluice,</hi> another againſt <hi>Broda,</hi> and the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Borghen,</hi> which ſhall increaſe as occaſion ſerues: but when <hi>Spinola</hi> vnderſtood, that many men were ſlaine by the fallies of the Garriſons in <hi>Berghen,</hi> who by this time hath 6000. ſouldiers in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he gaue order to retire his Army ſome halfe a mile from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ravelings, out of the danger of the ſhot, till hee came himſelf to direct them further, but by reaſon they haue not yet entrencht them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, it is very probable, they doe not determine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the ſiege long: but ſuddenly to riſe and goe to ſome other place.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Hage</hi> the Letters are as favorable in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the <hi>States,</hi> affirming, that there is now no going to <hi>Antwarp</hi> by the way of the River, becauſe the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> with their men of warre not onely watch the ſame: but haue new fortifications on the land of <hi>Fertoll:</hi> as for <hi>Berghen,</hi> they are confident both of the ſtrength of the place, and ſufficiency of the men, being all old ſouldiers, and very neere 8000. inſomuch that they make dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions vpon the Spaniards, as having their Portes open all night, and by their ſallies not onely put many of them to the ſword, but returne with great booty: ſo that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>Spinola's</hi> Armie makes approches, or attempts any on-ſet, then doe the Batteries of the Ravelings play vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and eyther enforce them backe, or kill them in the place.</p>
            <p>Some 4. dayes ſince it was ſuppoſed, they would riſe, wherupon the horſe of <hi>Breda</hi> trooped to overlooke them, and the Governour <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> (as I take it) of the houſe of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> ſent the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> word of their prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: but as it ſhould ſeeme, he is careleſſe of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and confident to overwatch them what courſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2745:11"/>they take, becauſe the Souldiers were never ſo willing to fight as at this houre, nor the <hi>States</hi> never ſo able to maintaine the Warre.</p>
            <p>Other Letters from ſeverall port Townes aſſure vs, that the <hi>Rochellers</hi> haue taken divers priſes, and intercepted ſome ſhips of ſouldiers, who haue ſent priſoners to <hi>Midel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borogh</hi> and other places.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2745:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
